{
  "reference_number": "9996",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "Mankind has mucked around for decades, there should be no more opportunity to veer off course now."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "It's time to get tough. It's the reality we have to face for the generations ahead."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions (including from new forest planting) and using some emissions reductions from overseas (international carbon units) that have strong environmental safeguards",
      "answer_index": 2,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "I would be happy to allow a tougher target to replace the original target though, but not allow a weaker target."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "No - emissions budgets should not be able to be changed",
      "answer_index": 9,
      "notes": "Having the option to change something implies that the goalposts can be moved and that is not good, because it allows us a cop out\n so to speak. The budget should only be changed if it is tougher than the one it is replacing."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The impact on poorer people should be structured in a way so that it's cheaper/easier for them to make the better choices for\nclimate change. For example, providing a reverse scale subsidy (cheaper cars get more of a subsidy than expensive cars) for them\n\nwhen it comes to purchasing an EV. Poor people can't afford to sponsor climate change initiatives as much as the wealthier people,\nbut the poorer people will be affected more. There needs to be real financial support to make it easy for the poor people to make the\n\nright decisions."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Businesses across the country and in all industries. This is a country effort, so there will need to be cross subsidisation to lessen the\nimpact on particular industries like airlines, farming and such."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Fighting climate change is going to cost truckloads of money. Every decision needs to be vetted by the Climate Change Commission.\nFor example, Dunedin is going to get a new hospital on the site of the old Cadbury's Chocolate Factory. This is a mistake as far as the\n\nsite is concerned and a waste of money. That site lacks elevation and will be one of the early victims of rising sea levels. The site for\nthe new hospital needs to be changed to higher ground. We need both the carrot and stick approach to take on the problem.\nPenalise those old school behaviours and reward the better ones. We need to shut down the Huntly power stations and get to 100\n\npercent renewable soon. We don't have any large scale solar generation in New Zealand though. EVs need more of an incentive. New\ncars are expensive and if we want to have mass uptake, there needs to be money thrown at them. Many countries have subsidies for\n\nnew EV purchase and all we do is waive the RUC and have some transit lane access in Auckland. Introduce a financial subsidy for new\nEV purchases. I have attached an example (picture) where only cars costing less than $100,000 can get a subsidy, which is capped\nat $5,000 per purchase. This would allow a greater uptake of EVs - I mean if somebody can afford to pay $100,000 for an EV, would a\n\n$1,000 subsidy be a deal breaker? Rather different if your car is costing you $30,000 and you can get a $5,000 subsidy! That could\nbe the difference between buy an EV vs. a petrol car. Have a look at Norway. The government threw lots of money towards EV\n\nownership - it was so good, they achieved their target 3 years ahead of schedule. It cost them a lot though, but EVs and hybrids sales\naccount for nearly 50% of all new vehicles in Norway."
    }
  ]
}
